If id known this earlier, I could have
saved myself a lot of sadness and
hardship.
If you hold the control key, the shift
key, and the T when you accidentally
close a web page or document, it'll
reload. Oh, right. But we're here about
the coffee and the tea. Uh, here's the
thing. A lot of people enjoy their
coffee and tea, and who am I to tell you
to stop? Not like most people would care
anyway, as we've been sucked into the
sweet embrace of caffeine addiction. But
there is a wrong way to consume both
that actually eliminates the positive
impacts of both on your health if you
care about that kind of thing. You see,
coffee and tea are filled with
polyphenols, molecules that have
multiple positive effects in our body.
For example, polyphenols will act as
antioxidants, meaning that they
eliminate damaging molecules called
reactive oxygen species, which otherwise
interact with components of the cell and
damage them. Not only that, polyphenols
reduce the activity of a major producer
of these reactive oxygen species called
NADPH oxidase. This is all going to
matter in a minute because these
polyphenols improve something called
flow mediated dilation. as in your blood
vessels will open allowing more blood
flow and by extension more nutrients to
the cells of the body. It also reduces
blood pressure thereby protecting you
from cardiovascular disease. The blood
vessel is able to do that through the
activity of an enzyme that can be turned
off by excess reactive oxygen species.
It's called enos. If enos is active,
like when free polyphenols are around,
it produces more nitric oxide, a potent
molecule that widens the blood vessel
and more flow mediated dilation.
However, if nitric oxide interacts with
reactive oxygen species, it turns into a
harmful peroxy nitrite that also damages
the structures around it, reducing flow
mediated dilation. The short of it is
that uh the ability for your body to be
more responsive. So have greater
adaptability in flow mediated dilation
that's linked to better health. So
researchers fed participants either
water or tea to measure changes in flow
mediated dilation. And as we can see
here, there's the water condition, the
tea condition, and the mysterious third
condition that I will reveal shortly. If
the bars go up, that's an increase in
flow mediated dilation. Clearly the tea
increased flow mediated dilation
multiple fold. But this blue bar knocks
down the effect to nothing again. Turns
out that condition is the exact same tea
but mixed with milk. So why is milk
causing tea to lose its effectiveness?
And is this also the case with coffee?
Well, here's the thing. It's believed
that polyphenols can bind proteins like
those in milk that ultimately makes them
inert. So, does this affect coffee, too?
Well, there's certainly similar
polyphenols in coffee, but there's a
unique effect in coffee when mixed with
milk. Before we get to that, there's
additional data on how different
proteins affect this process, as well as
more data coming from these studies. If
you're interested, check out the full
analysis in the Physionic Insiders. Or
if you might be uh more interested, I
have hundreds more of these analyses,
including quick 30-second summaries that
could be delivered to your inbox on a
weekly basis. That includes some work on
the optimal amounts of coffee and tea
for health benefits and more specifics
on the mechanisms of coffeey's
healthpromoting effects and so much
more. Come on, feed your addiction and
strengthen your bias. I can help you
there. Okay, what about coffee and the
nasty nasty milks?
In this second study, researchers
measured the bioavailability of the most
potent polyphenols in coffee,
chlorogenic acid, by measuring the
urinary excretion over 24 hours after
consuming a standard cup of coffee. So,
the greater the excretion, the more was
absorbed. If we look at that data, we
can see the 24 hours broken up by time
blocks. And we can see that the amount
of excretion of CGA, that's chlorogenic
acid on the vertical axis. The higher
the bar, the better. Then we have our
trusty water condition and the coffee
alone and the coffee with milk. If we
look at the excretion, it's elevated in
both coffee conditions for the first 4
hours. But then the milk condition,
while still experiencing an increase in
these polyphenols, lags behind the
coffee only condition. That implies that
milk is reducing the bioavailability of
chlorogenic acid. So, it's likely not
being absorbed. These data along with
the tea data indicates that milk seems
to reduce the levels of beneficial
molecules found in coffee and tea. But
there's more to the story. Here's the
thing. In either of these studies, the
researchers are looking at short-term
measures. We're talking 24 hours.
They're also using acute measures like
flow mediated dilation which can change
in the short term but then not reflect
long-term effects. A great example is
exercise which can reduce flow mediated
dilation temporarily but then increase
it later as well as is known to be
robustly related to positive health
outcomes. The unfortunate aspect here,
although I looked, I couldn't find any
long-term studies over decades looking
at these drinks with and without milk
and actual outcomes like cancer rates or
cardiovascular disease events and so on.
I found one that separated black coffee
from coffee with uh additives, but the
additives included sugar, so not a fair
or clean comparison. That leaves us with
some mechanistic data, which is, as I've
shouted from the rooftops, a weak
foundation for lasting arguments without
clinical outcomedriven data. That isn't
even to mention the minuscule sample
size for one of these studies. Still,
there is some evidence across multiple
polyphenols that there's reduced uptake
of these polyphenols. That isn't
anything to ignore, especially when
other studies referenced by the
researchers indicate similar results. If
you're watching the insider version of
this analysis, I'll have more to say on
that front. So, where does that leave
us? Well, listen. If you really enjoy
milk in your coffee or tea, go be free.
Do not let some know-it-all PhD keep you
from your dreams. We accept milk
drinkers and pure drinkers alike here at
Physionic. But if you're especially
worried about getting the best bang for
your buck, this weak evidence indicates
consuming coffee and tea plain, pure,
and unmuddied is superior to the lowly
milk drinkers.
You fell for my non-judgment, you fool.
Then fall into this next video. Were
nonjudgmental there, too. Pinky promise.